when we consider the philosophical
investigations of the 20th century we
understand that not all 20th century
philosophy has been dedicated to
existentialism
there have been other schools that we
will look at in our last session but in
the main there's been much concern in
the 20th century to focus attention on
the relationship between logic
and language
and also in addition to that the
relationship of these subjects to modern
science and particularly with respect to
mathematics
because the field of mathematics we've
already seen historically all the way
back to Plato and the pythagoreans and
up through the modern period with
Descartes and Spinoza and leibniz has
made a profound impact on the world of
thought
and there's one man who stands out in
the 20th century
as a giant in the field of mathematics
who also wrote
voluminously in the field of philosophy
and he of course is the British
philosopher mathematician Bertrand
Russell
now most of Russell's important Works
took place in the first half of the 20th
century and he became known popularly in
his old age in the second half of the
20th century for his outspoken
demonstrations that he led in England
against the use of atomic weapons
and and because of some of the extreme
positions that Professor Russell took
some people dismissed him as a crazy old
man
but his work in the technical field of
math and philosophy certainly belies
that negative evaluation of him
now one of the things I'm most concerned
about with respect to Russell and his
impact on our generation of people
is the popular work that he did
he wrote a little
best-selling book
entitled why I am not a Christian
now before I get into that I have to say
that Bertrand Russell did not consider
himself a convinced atheist
he claimed to be an agnostic because he
said no one could philosophically
scientifically or logically demonstrate
the non-existence of God
and yet at the same time he said we
cannot demonstrate the existence of God
and so he preferred to suspend judgment
but he was
particularly critical of historic
Christianity and historic three theism
and he leveled basically three principal
objections against
theism in general and Christianity in
particular and I want to take some time
today to go over those three objections
the first objection he raised against
historic theism
was
based on a critique of the cosmological
argument
like Kant who had raised questions about
the traditional arguments of God
Bertrand Russell saw that the
cosmological argument for the existence
of God Rest rested upon
inferences drawn from the law of
causality
and in his book why I'm not a Christian
Russell relates the experience he had as
a teenager
when he first wrote the writings I'm
sorry he first read the writings of John
Stuart Mill
and Mill had a profound influence upon
Russell's thinking
he relates in this anecdote that going
into his later teenage years
Russell believed in the existence of God
based upon the simple reasoning and
inference that the world as he perceived
it required ultimately a first cause
and he reasoned causal causally and
cosmologically back
to the Creator from his observations of
the creation which is the standard
approach with the use of the so-called
cosmological argument because it is a
reason or an argument based upon the
cosmos demanding a sufficient cause for
its being
but when he was 17 or 18 years old he
read this critique by John Stuart Mill
regarding causality and Mill made the
observation
that if everything
that is
requires a Cause
that not only would the universe require
a Cause
but God himself would require a Cause
and if God required a cause then
whatever it was that caused God would
likewise
require a cause add infinitum
and so Mill argued against the
cosmological argument on the basis of
The Logical possibility of an infinite
regress that is the idea of an infinite
series of finite causes
now
Russell considered that Insight that he
gleaned from Mill to be something of an
epiphany
and he said that that controlled his
thinking with respect to the existence
of God literally for the rest of his
life
so it was a philosophical argument that
he heard as a teenager that turned him
from a theist into an agnostic
again based upon the possibility that he
saw for an infinite regress or an
infinite series of finite causes
now
the problem if I may interject a brief
critique at this point
is that
uh Russell made the same error
with respect to the cosmological
argument that John Stuart Mill had made
and Mill passed the error on to Russell
and neither one of these great mental
Giants ever realized
the obvious error that they were making
and the error of course was in their
understanding of
causality and the law of cause and
effect
because the law of cause and effect does
not assert or maintain that everything
must have a Cause
rather the law of causality as we've
seen declares that every effect
must have an antecedent cause
and as sharp as Russell was in the
application of principles of logic and
Mathematics to philosophy frankly he
should have noticed the difference in
definition here and he would have seen
that the classic definition of the law
of cause and effect is an analytically
true statement because the statement is
true by definition
to say that every effect must have a
Cause
is the same as saying every triangle
must have three sides because an effect
by definition
is that which has an antecedent cause
and a cause cannot be a cause without
producing an effect an effect cannot be
in effect without having been caused so
the law of causality is merely a formal
extension of the law of
non-contradiction
and is a logical necessity
now it's one thing to say that every
effect
must have a cause it's quite another to
say that everything that is must have a
cause because that second statement
presupposes that everything that is
an effect
but the whole point of Christian theism
is that God is not an effect that he is
not caused by something prior to him or
outside of him but that he has the power
of existence or the power of being in
and of himself
eternally
and from a logical perspective the
concept of self-existent Eternal being
violates no rule of math or of logic it
is a perfectly legitimate rational idea
the idea of an uncaused effect is a
perfectly irrational idea and it is
falsified because it is false by
definition
so it amazes me that Bertrand Russell as
sharp as he was missed that critical
distinction
all of his life
but the second argument that he gave
against theism was closely related to
the first and is also one that had been
championed earlier by John Stuart Mill
and that
was the argument
that the existence of God
is made Highly Questionable because of
the presence of suffering
and pain
in the world
and this Mill had stated it earlier if
God is a being who is described as being
good and loving
and all-powerful
those attributes cannot be squared with
the presence of suffering in this world
because if he's all powerful and does
not alleviate or eliminate suffering
then he is not good
if he is all good or perfectly righteous
and doesn't eliminate suffering
because he lacks the ability to do so
then he would not be omnipotent so the
naked presence of pain and suffering in
this world would eliminate either God's
goodness or his power
and that argument was used as I said by
Mill and then repeated by
by Russell now of course
the weight of that difficulty
and of that dilemma is one that has been
keenly felt by many people historically
and certainly by persons in the
scriptures themselves as the psalmist
raised the question why do the wicked
prosper and the righteous suffer
the whole book of Job wrestles with the
problem of human suffering as it relates
to the goodness of God
and yet historic judeo-christianity
sees the presence of pain and suffering
in this world
not
as a contradiction
of the righteous omnipotence of God but
rather of evidence for the righteous
omnipotence of God
because the explanation for the presence
of pain and suffering in this world
rests in the biblical concept of the
fall of the human race
that is that with the presence of moral
evil
and the violation of the righteous
standards of God
the whole world and everyone in it is
now made subject to pain to suffering
and to death
not because God is bad
but because he is good
and as a good God he is obliged to
punish the evil actions of his creatures
so always in scripture the presence of
suffering and death in the world are
linked to sin and to God's righteous
Judgment of that sin
to suppose that a judge
eliminates punishment
altogether
is not to attribute goodness to the
judge but wickedness
because the judge if he is to be just
will not reward evil
but will punish it
but we have to say one thing more that
the biblical view is that suffering and
pain are in the world because it is part
of the consequences of the world's
fallenness and yet at the same time
we are warned in Scripture
to understand that that's presence of
pain and suffering is not God's final
word
he does subject his world to suffering
to pain and to death
but he is not only the judge of the
world he is also its Redeemer
and the most astonishing dimension of
redemption in biblical terms is that
that Redemption is brought to pass
through the willing and voluntary
subjection and submission to pain to
suffering and death in the life of the
Son of God and it was out of God's love
and concern for his people that he
provides an Avenue of redemption for
them from this suffering and Pain by
having his son
embrace it and take it upon himself
which is often overlooked in this
but the third argument that Russell used
in this case specifically to refute the
truth claims of the Bible and of
Christianity in particular
is
the teaching of Jesus
that is recorded in all three synoptic
gospels in what is known as the Olivet
discourse
a discourse that I spent a whole book
dealing with in the last days According
To Jesus
but Russell along with others of his
generation
objected to the biblical claims of being
the word of God
and to the claims that Jesus
Not only was not the Messiah but was not
even a true Prophet because Jesus made
predictions
that are recorded in all three of the
synoptic gospels that failed to come to
pass within the specific time frame that
Jesus gave to them
and of course Russell points to the
Olivet discourse wherein Jesus standing
by the temple said to his disciples that
not one stone of this Temple will be
left upon another
and he predicted the absolutely
Unthinkable to his contemporaries in
Jerusalem namely that the temple itself
would be destroyed and even worse
that Mount Zion the holy city of God
Jerusalem
would be destroyed
the Jews
would be dispersed
and the holy city
would be captured and trodden underfoot
by gentiles
and that's not something that somebody
would predict in the early part of the
first century on the basis of
geopolitical prognostications this was
an absolutely Unthinkable
series of events that Jesus predicted
which of course
came to pass with astonishing
and particular accuracy with the
destruction of the temple under the
forces of the Roman general Titus who
later became emperor
in ad70
when Titus laid waste not only to the
temple
but to the whole city of Jerusalem
and over a million Jews were slaughtered
in that great Holocaust of the first
century and the Jewish people who
survived were
dispersed the Nations all over the world
and your newspapers today still
describe the volatile situation that
surrounds the relationship of that piece
of real estate in the Mideast to this
ethnic group of people
who are called Jews
but in any case as accurate as that
prediction was the problem was in the
midst of that same passage of Prophecy
Jesus spoke of his return
of his coming
and of catastrophic events that would
indicate it signs that would take place
such as wars and rumors of wars of
earthquakes and of an apostasy and of
false Messiahs arising in the land and
then describe the end that was to come
to pass in terms of astronomical
upheavals and perturbations of the
moon's the sun being blotted out and
darkness and the heavens rolling up and
all of that sort of language that we
find there
and all that that's fine so far except
that as Russell pointed out
Jesus clearly predicted
in that context
when his disciples raised the obvious
question that anybody would raise after
hearing these dire predictions and
catastrophic forecasts from Jesus they
said to him teacher when will these
things happen
when will these things take place
and in direct response to that question
Jesus said to his disciples
this generation will not pass away
until all of these things be fulfilled
not all together unlike
similar statements that Jesus made on
other occasions when he said some of you
will not taste death
till all of these things come to pass or
you will not go over all of the cities
of Israel until you see the kingdom of
God coming and so on
and so
Russell looks at that text and he says
anybody
who reads that obviously if they're
honest will understand that Jesus
predicted not only the destruction of
Jerusalem and the temple within the
space of 40 years or so the time of one
generation but also his own return
at the end of the age and even though
his predictions were right with respect
to Jerusalem and the temple they were
obviously incorrect with respect to the
description of his own return
and so Russell along with many critics
of the 19th century concluded that the
Bible is false and that Jesus at best
was a false prophet who missed the mark
with respect to the time frame of these
forecasts
again this is the subject of a book that
I have written a whole book about these
time frame references
and I believe that Jesus in that
situation was not talking about his
coming at the end of history but his
coming in judgment upon Israel at the
end of the Jewish age which corresponded
with the fall of Jerusalem and the
destruction of the Temple
that's a very complex matter but for
those of you who are interested in it
you can read my book or others who have
also seen this as the central theme of
the book of Revelation in the early
Church of the visitation of the day of
the Lord the day of Darkness for Israel
and it was the Judgment coming of God
upon that nation that took place in 70
A.D but in any case Russell's
agnosticism
has permeated
not only the realm of science but the
realm of philosophy and has even
impacted theology in the 20th century